Hey guys, Shandide welcome back to the
channel and let's start today with the
fall tolerant microservices part two. So
in part one we have already seen about
rate limiter and uh if you have not seen
it kindly have a look because that's uh
you will understand what is actually
fault tolerant microservices are. So
today we will start with the bulk ahead
and see what are the various use cases
it supports. That's also very important
like when we are going to build the
bulkhead.
So very quick rate limiter it protects
our application from clients. This is
why I am telling you again about rate
limiter in just 1 minute is because
clear distinction need to be present
between rate limiter and bulkhead
because many time a confusion happens
like which one is bulkhead which one is
rate limiter. So focus here is that rate
limiter protects our application. Let's
say our application is order. It
protects our application from whom? From
clients. So let's say this is my client
and client is sending me too many
requests. So it limited limit them. Hey,
how many requests we can accept within a
specific window. Right?
And also one more thing is rate limiter
never talks about concurrency. So just
rate li rate limiter says that hey I can
accept 10 request
in 1 minute. Either you can send me 10
requests in one shot or one by one. It
never talks about concurrency. It just
says that what is the limit. Okay. But
it protect us from our clients.
Now let's go to the bulkhead that it
helps to control how many concurrent
requests can go to downstream service.
Now let's say this is our service order.
Now I am more concerned about the
request which I am sending to my
downstream.
Now I am not concerning about the
request which I'm getting from my
clients.
Okay. So that is one of the major
difference and bulkhead majorly talks
about the concurrent request. We will
see that and if we understand this two
use cases right. So there are two
possible use cases. If you understand
the two use cases
no matter when a interviewer or in your
implementation like a scenario is put
you would be able to clearly understand
that whether rate limiter or bulkhead
need to be applied. So understand that
one is very very simple use case. Let's
say you have order. This is your
component and this is your downstream
product. So order invokes product API.
Let's say product is a small and
lightweight service and can only handle
three concurrent requests. Okay. And
product itself is like very lightweight.
It doesn't have put rate limiter on
itself. Okay.
But
with the bulk ahead you can control
that. Okay. So you know that product can
handle only three concurrent request at
a time. Okay. So it accept three
requests all at the same time. But when
the fourth comes no there is no thread
left. So when any one of them get free
then the another request would get
fulfilled.
Okay. So this is very very simple use
case very simple use case and this use
case is resolved through simma 4
bulkhead. So there are two types of
bulkhead.
One is simma 4 bulkhead we have seen
another one I'm going to tell but for
this use case whenever interviewer put
this use case simma for bulkhead is the
answer. Okay we will see it how it
functionality
but I think this is clear right?
Whenever there is a condition that
uh you have a downstream which can only
accept this many concurrent requests how
you can handle it through simma for
bulkhead.
Okay. Another use case, very very
important use case. And also remember
that before I go to this use case,
remember one very very important
system design problem which is like a
noisy neighbor
problem.
If you can recall this problem what it
says that let's say this is your
application
and you have application have multiple
tenants
tenant
one tenant two tenant three.
So let's say that you have one of the
tenant which is very very noisy like the
traffic from this tenant is so
high that it consume all resources
all resources and even the tenants which
are not like
uh sending that much traffic or let's
say they are just hitting one call but
their request is denied because all of
your resources are used by one tenant.
That is known as noisy neighbor problem.
That you have one neighbor which is very
noisy or very very similar but you can
say that the context is very uh narrow
in this use case. Noisy neighbor context
is big like it includes thread
infrastructure
resources
DB like everything. If your tenant is
res using the resources like consider
everything DB resource infrastructures
threads everything but here we are
mostly talking about thread in this use
case now consider this use case you will
find very very similarity to noisy
neighbor but the context is again I'm
telling it's very narrow noisy neighbor
problem context is very broader
so let's say that API API 1 makes a
downstream call to product service. So I
have so this is our component order is
our component and we have API 1 which
when it get invoked it make a call to
product service. Product service is very
fast right? Product service returns the
response in less than 100 millisecond
only. So it's a very fast service. Okay.
Now we have API 2
and when this API got invoked it
actually invokes internally payment
service. Now this payment service is
slow. It might take 5 second to process
a request. Let's say it has to further
go to third party uh endpoint but this
is slow this is slow service and for API
1 the product is fast service. This is
our setup. Now let's say what if there
is a sudden spike in API 2 traffic. What
if there's a sudden spike in API 2
traffic and it internally invoked the
payment
component which is slow. Now your thread
got blocked for 5 second. Thread one got
blocked for 5 second. Thread two got
blocked for 5 seconds. Similarly your
nth threads got blocked for 5 seconds.
Okay. So when a sudden spike comes in
API 2, more and more calls are made to
payment service which is slow and it is
possible that they might not be a
concurrent but since this is a slow
service it blocks your thread longer for
5 second and more and it possible that
your all threads of order service are
now blocked. So let's say it has a
thread pool of 10 threads and there is a
certain spike comes in API 2. All 10
threads are now blocked here.
Okay. So there is no thread here. Just
assume that. Now if any request comes to
API 1. Okay. And this API 1 will it be
able to fulfill it? No. There is no
thread left
in the thread pool.
So either it has to wait or it will get
rejected.
So even though
it invokes a very fast service there is
not much traffic to API 1 but still it
gets suffer because of API 2.
So you can say that
we can so you remember there is a ship
concept so in a ship there are different
compartments.
So if water fills up into one of the
compartment they block it so that water
do not spill over into rest of the
compartment. So very very similar
concept is used in the use case two if
your so they will put a limit they will
put a limit or you can say that thread
pool so they limit a threads hey API 2
they I know that you are invoking an
endpoint which is very slow
so I give you only max five threads
let's say you can't use more threads
than that
okay so even though I have total 10
threads in my order thread pool we I
have only allocated five threads to API
2 not more than that
okay so I have and if let's say suddenly
more requests coming in the API to more
than five either they have to waited or
get rejected because the max I can
allocate is fifth so you can say that
similar to this one I have provided a
limit
okay so that only resource I can provide
you man.
Okay. So that my other endpoint do not
suffer.
So you understand this use case.
Whenever we have multiple endpoint and
one of the end point we have to make
sure that it do not consume all the
resources
then bulkhead can be used and it has a
thread pool bulk ahead type. So this is
the second type of bulkhead thread pool
bulkhead through which we can limit the
resource to a particular endpoint.
Okay. So we'll see that also.
So these are the two types. Sema for
bulkhead threadpool bulkhead. Let's go
one by one. So sema for bulkhead
limit the number of concurrent calls
using counter.
Okay. So you have this API,
you have this product service.
So max three concurrent calls, fourth
one should be rejected. So at a time
three calls can go into your critical
section.
You can say that critical section.
Critical section here is the one where
we are invoking the API.
The one where we are invoking the API.
Consider that that is our critical
section. So three calls are allowed,
three threads are allowed, the fourth
thread it has to wait till one of them
get is free. Okay. So if you understand
the bul if you need to understand the
bulkhead understand more like a thread
pools and all. So in that case
it would be easy to understand. So when
I say that three calls so just that only
we have a three threads. Okay. So only
three concurrent request max can go to
this critical section. The fourth one it
will get rejected because there is no
thread left.
Now why the name simma 4? Because the
counter how it manage that only three
requests can go. So it uses a sema 4
locking strategy. So if you following
the Java playlist also in that
multi-threading series I have told about
the sema 4 locks. In that I have
explained like how simma 4
manage the counter that allow three
calls or four calls or five calls
whatever the number we will give that
many
request can goes into a critical
section.
So internally it uses a sema 4 lock.
Okay. So kindly have a look if you have
any doubt with the simma 4 how a simma 4
locking works how it allow
n number of concurrent calls. Okay
so in short limit the number of
concurrent call using counter and here
internally it uses simma for log if the
limit is reached further calls are
rejected immediately or block for a
specific wait time. Let's see that the
first thing first like we did in the
rate limiter we have to add a dependency
only we have to add a dependency of
resilience 4j that's all because
resilience 4j provide us multiple fall
tolerance like rate limiter bulk ahead
retry circuit breaker and all so we
don't have to individually download the
dependencies resilience forj dependency
is enough
this is just a controller like we have
normal no change the f client I am using
yeah so controller is invoking the
product service method invoke product
API okay so let's say that this is the
place where I'm actually invoking my
other application product
here it has one endpoint API okay and
this is my order component
and
I am trying to invoke the product call
that's the this.
So here I'm just invoking it very normal
using faint line no nothing difference
but now this annotation I have put on
top of it at the rate bulk ahead uh
bulkhead
give a name to this what is the type of
bulkhead you want to use so I want to
use bulkhead type dot sema 4
okay and what is the fallback method
if there is any thing happen. Let's say
that Sema 4 if it reached the limit
three concurrent request fourth comes
which get uh either cued or failed. So
once it is failed it move to the fall
back method this one.
Now what will happen here is also uh so
this one is simple right we have to just
put annotation we will see how it works.
So now let's see that
application.properties
in application.properties we have to put
resilience 4j.bulcad bulk.instance
the name we have given here the bulkhead
name what is the maximum concurrent call
is two maximum concurrent call means
maximum
concurrent threads
are allowed into a critical section so
this is considered my critical section
maximum threads can go inside which can
invoke the product API
Okay. So maximum I want is two not more
than that. And there is something called
max weight duration. Currently I put it
zero means fail it immediately. Don't
even wait it. If there is no thread left
fail it immediately and call the product
fallback method. But if you want that
hey it should not fail immediately then
you can provide some values here like
so you can provide like 500 ms
millisecond 1 second like this. So you
can provide in ms is for millisecond s
for second m for minute h for hours d
for delay. So here if you see if wait
time is zero reject immediately wait
time you can also give 300 millisecond
2 second 1 minute like this you can
define based on like how much time you
want a particular thread to wait before
it get rejected immediately
make sense
so this I told you that this everything
is handled by AOP AOP add runtime proxy
code. Okay. So when this annotation is
seen by AOP, it add a proxy code and it
knows that it has a SIMA 4 and this is a
code and it will use this SIM 4 locking
strategy. It just add a code for the
SIMA 4 lock. How the Sema 4 lock is
implemented. So if you see this simma 4
functionality right you will easily get
to know how this concurrency handled.
Okay,
I will put into the description section
also that the link for this uh video. So
you can check the simma 4 part only so
that it will get clear to you.
But simma 4 bulkhead is clear right? Why
exactly it is used for.
Okay.
Now see the threadpool bulkhead. So
again one thing is in thread pool
bulkhead we are managing what we are
limiting one of our
API you can say that or a critical
section place so that it don't consume
all the resource so it is calling this
it is calling this let's say so I'm
limiting this that hey when you are
invoking this downstream
use only this much resource you can't
use all the resource or all the threats
Okay. So that my other endpoints or my
other my complete as a whole application
should not get affected because of this.
So assign a dedicated thread pool for
each service.
E service means let's say you have a
payment service like this endpoint is
invoking a payment service. You can
provide a dedicated
thread pool for this. If you have let's
say sales order is calling sales service
you can provide a dedicated thread pool
like okay okay you can use this much
resource only if you're invoking this
downstream service
okay only that pool is used to call the
downstream
very important it is only for the
okay
but first thing first as the name thread
pool bulk ahead
what it is using thread pool again in
the Java the whole dedicated video of
thread pool and thread pool executor I
have created very in depth I have
explained how exactly thread pools works
so kindly have a look like it will help
you understand like what internally AOP
might be doing how it is creating a
thread pool how it is adding a task into
a thread pool so thread pool has let's
say task Initial task uh initial threads
let's say four threads also it has a
queue of size particular size n so task
has to be submitted and once it is
submitted if there is no thread will it
put here or it will reject it so we have
all the point discussed here. So kindly
have a look of thread pool then it would
be little bit more clear how internally
AOP might be doing it.
So here
if you see its implementation nothing
much difference.
So here
the order service where we are invoking
the product API. So you can say that
this is our critical section.
Okay. I want to limit that only limited
number of threads goes inside.
Okay. So I have put at the bulkhead.
Give it a name of this bulkhead.
bulkhead type which I'm using is thread
pool. The fallback is this method.
Okay. Now I am using a thread pool means
you know that thread pool has a
configuration. What is the minimum
number of threads? What is the maximum
number of threads?
Okay. So that's we have to define what
is the Q capacity. So in
application.properties properties like
this we can define those thread pool
properties resilience 4j thread pool
bulk ahead instances the name this is
the name right
so core thread pool size is the threads
which will always be present into a
thread pool three maximum thread pool is
three also okay so generally what happen
is let's say if the you can say that
minimum like core is two and maximum is
three. Let's say the Q size is your two
or let's say Q size is four.
So 1 2 3 4 four spaces. So let's say
this thread is busy. This thread is
busy. This thread is busy. So both the
threads are busy. Request one it is
fulfilling. It is request two it is
fulfilling. If any further requests come
then Q would be used. Then request three
would be put here. Request four, request
five, request six. Okay. So total six
requests here. Now request seven comes.
Now there is no thread currently pending
because the minimum thread pool or core
thread pool is two and both are
working. Q is full. Will it reject the
request? No. Because max thread pool
size let's say is three. So means it
will create new thread and request 7
work on that. Now if eight comes
does any thread there in the thread
pool? No. Is any Q has a space? No. Does
the max limit reach? Yes. Maximum is
three. Three threads are already
working. So now this will be rejected.
So I have already explained everything
into this one. So this is just a very
quick brief so that you can recall what
is minimum thread pool, max thread pool,
Q capacity. So based on this
configuration it actually creates a
thread pool. How to create a thread
pool? You will get understand when you
see this.
Now here if you see AOP proxy intercept
your method call. Okay. So with the
bulkhead it know it intercept your
method call. So it submits your method
to bulkhead thread pool configured via
application.properties.
So consider this internally AOP might be
doing like this completable future. A
sync. So this supply a sync actually
submit your request to a thread pool.
Submit your request to thread pool.
Okay. and the whole method
body uh is submitted as a task. So this
whole method
right whatever so currently here I am
only my critical section is the place
downstream API which I am calling. So
you need to make sure very very specific
that where you are putting this
annotation. So whatever the u business
logic validation you have within this
method right that would be submitted.
Okay. So use it very carefully that only
downstream call should be present into
this because bulkhead is mostly
applicable for the downstream only
controlling the downstream
right how much resource I can use while
calling the downstream.
Okay. So you know that here in the
thread pool this is how this is the way
of submitting the request to a thread uh
thread pool. So supply a sync and then
you put
the your method logic the whole method
body runs here right and which thread
pool executor it will has to use. So it
will use bulkhead thread pool exeutor
which it will create using this
configuration.
So one thing important is that it
returns completable future object. It
returns completable future object. Why?
Because internally AOP intercepting it
and AOP going to submit the request to a
thread pool and the way to submit a
request is this completable future. try
a sync because the request might has to
wait either in Q or it will get accepted
one thread would be allocated to it
which will start work and it will return
the completable future object okay and
that thread will continue working it. So
the same thing is since uh
we are not writing the code AOP is
writing it but the concept in behind the
same it is doing the same we get a
completable future object and the AOP
also returns a completable future only
so that's why it want a return type
computable future
okay and whatever the fallback method we
will write also it should match we have
already discussed in the rate limiter so
that's why I have a return type
similarly here only here it is also
string string only thing is it has
throwable extra
okay so you can test it like uh I have
just added system outprint ln here just
for the testing of this one like u so I
have just put it like which thread name
which thread is currently fulfilling
this
method call right so currently we have a
thread pool size is three and Q is two.
This is what we have defined right
initially. So here if you see let me
clarify a bit. So here if you see
what is the thread pool size three and
max is also three. So maximum we have
three threads only and the Q is only
two. So here if you see
I invoke the API six times. So six time
I invoke my endpoint.
So order controller I have invoked order
controller is invoking the invoke
product API.
So six times I have invoked the API. So
it means internally
so my controller
my service
and this is the product API.
Okay. 1 2 3 4 5 six time I invoke. So
sixth time they call service method you
can say that my critical section where
my logic is there to invoke the product
API.
So sixth time it might have tried to
tried to invoke product API but let's
see the behavior.
So first time I have three threads and
two Q. So first time request comes so
six calls right.
So first one is given to thread one. So
this one is getting fulfilled by thread
one. Second request is fulfilled by
thread two.
Second request is fulfilled by thread
two. So there are three threads right?
So thread three fulfilled the request
three. So see the name bulk ahead
product service three. So it is using my
product instance right. So it using my
thread pool whatever we have created
thread pool for product service it is
not using the common one
which is for the my order application.
No whatever I have created specifically
for my downstream it is using that
thread pool this one. So this is also a
you can validate that's why I'm printing
the thread name right.
So thread one, thread two, thread three
is also fulfilling. So now all three
threads are busy. They are fulfilling
three requests. Now request four and
request five. This four and five there
is no thread left. So it would be
inserted into Q.
Okay. And the sixth one the my all three
threads are busy. Q is full with request
four and five and the request six will
get rejected. So request six got
rejected. Product service is busy. Okay.
So it got rejected.
Now once two thread got free, it will
pick from my queue. Request four and
request five will get fulfilled either
by thread one or thread two. So thread
one become free. It pick request four.
Thread two become free it become request
five.
So exact thread pool functionality no
difference. whatever we have implemented
thread pool right into plain Java
internally spring AOP just doing that
only it is writing that code for us just
this is the configuration
and only thing is like uh this is our
task like this is the task it's submit
to a thread for processing that's all
okay Yeah. So this is uh
very important part. Um so here yeah one
very important thing. Yeah I wanted to I
was looking for that one. So here
let me clarify a bit uh a little bit let
me delete the writing so that it is
clearly visible. Yeah focus on this
part. when I am submitting a task here
right I am putting completable future
dot completed future
and this
here never do supply a sync so we if you
know thread pool you know that in plain
java we are doing this completable
future dotsupply a sync and internally
it will submit a task to a thread pool
this will submit the task to thread
And who should do it? AOP should do it.
And AOP is doing that. AOP internally
submit this. So we should not do supply
or sync here. We can we have to use
completed future here. So completed
future is doing nothing. It is a wrapper
like whatever your task. So this is my
actually a task which I want
uh to be submitted to a thread pool
actually. Okay.
But
I can't do because return type is
completable future. I just can't have
this. I have I can't just uh return a
string. I can't just return a string
because return type is completable
future. So I have to wrap it up. So I
have to wrap it up inside a completable
future object. That's all. So completed
future
do not submit the task to thread pool.
It only wrap the output. That's all. So
never use supply async here. So if you
just if you want to do testing right
just do completable future dossupply as
sync and just submit this. Okay. And
also uh just print the thread pool name
just what is the thread name right
before submitting just put a thread
name. So like here let's say you are
doing dot supply async and this product
by id product client by product by id
something something and you have a
thread name and just see that does your
bulcat thread pool used or not it will
not
because now you are submitting the
request when you are submitting the
request to a thread pool you are using a
thread from your order application
right your order application you are
using it.
So you need to use AOP because AOP will
now have the proper understanding that
okay when the bulkhead annotation is
used this is the name this is the
service then I have to look for
application.properties properties
and whatever the name you have provided
for the bulkhead that bulcad
particular name in configuration I have
to root read I have to create a thread
pool and use that. So AOP does that for
us and do supply async method and pass
the thread pool executor
along with it.
Okay. So if you just create supply a
sync and provide the method it will use
default one default one for your order
application or either you have to
manually handle that you have to
manually create a thread pool and pass
your bulkhead
bulkhead thread pool executor
then it will use this pool. But you have
to create now first executor
bulkhead exeutor you have to create
first for this all configuration you
have to create that this is the max this
is the min this is the Q once the
executor is created now if you are
calling the supply a sync supply a sync
then provide the task which you want to
submit let's say this is the task of
calling the downstream and then in the
comma the executor you have to pass this
executor you have to pass
then it will work fine because now you
are creating a executor you are passing
you are submitting supplier a sync you
are submitting to a thread pool and you
are also tell which executor to use now
it will not use the common one but if
you just simply do supply a sync and the
task calling the downstream let's say
this one it will use common thread pool
and you don't have to manually create a
executor Because this add the rate bulk
ahead ultimately internally going to do
the same thing. It will first create
threadpool executor and then call supply
async and pass your this task
and how it threadpool exeutor is created
and all it's all discussed here in dep
in description section I will put this
thing
got it
so last 1 minute let's see uh time
limiter because I am not going to cover
the time limiter reason being is that
time limiter is used to prevent a sync
call from hanging indefinitely.
Okay, time limiter is nonblocking in
resilience 4j means it is designed for a
synchronous operation
that returns a reactive type like
monoflux. So you remember that in a
blocking. So here if you remember in the
faint client
so faint client rest template rest
client these are all blocking calls
means threads are waiting and the thread
should not wait indefinitely. They
should not hang indefinitely. So we have
provided that connection timeout and ret
time out. We have already seen that in
the flland example. So we provided right
connection timeout how much time it take
to make a HTTP
uh TCP connection
read timeout how much time I should wait
before I get a response from the
downstream. So only this much time it
will wait it will not wait indefinitely.
So for blocking calls we can handle it
through this. But what about using calls
right? Let's say you fire and forget.
This is you fire and forget. Now assing
there is a thread in it is working. How
you make sure that it don't hang or
continuously work indefinitely.
So that thread should get also freed up.
Okay. So that's where time limiter is
used. So I will cover it when we will
cover the web flux reactive programming
in that it will make more sense because
in the blocking rest template rest
client it does not make sense because it
is non-blocking in resilience 4j
okay even if you put into non-blocking
let's say at the rate time limiter okay
so what it will happen is you call you
submit a request you submit a task to a
thread pool Okay. And your thread got
freed and now async thread is working.
So it will not ultimately free this up.
It will just try to free your this thing
which is automatically get freed. It
just submit a task to a thread pool and
just finish move ahead. Now thising
thread is working.
So here in the
blocking mechanism
it will not be able to free this async
call.
So we will ultimately see when we will
start the web flux.
Okay.
So if there is any doubt let me know in
the comment section. We can discuss
further. But please practice this with
hand like play with this configuration
debug it and you will understand better.
Right? And I would say that if you are
not familiar with thread pool and this
get it more uh like have a look at once
please because then you will get clearly
understand that what AOP might be doing
inside how it is creating a thread pool
executor and how it is submitting a
request to a thread pool.
Okay. Okay guys thank you. Have a good
day. Bye.